DAN KLEIN: So before we figure out how
to do search in the presence of
actions, whose outcomes are uncertain,
we should think why would we ever be
in this situation?
Is this just some weird
thing that happens?
Well, there's a lot of reasons why you
could have uncertainty as to the
outcome of your action.
Sometimes there is explicit
randomness.
And in the case of games, this
is often intentionally there.
For example, you may actually roll
some dice while playing a game.
That's a case where you are explicitly
taking an action kind of for the whole
purpose of injecting randomness
into the process.
But that's not really everything.
Sometimes your opponents
are unpredictable.
For example, there might be some
randomness into how a ghost respond.
But in the real world, it's
even more than that.
It's the fact that when you take an
action, you're never really sure
what's going to happen.
For example, if you're doing robot
motion and you tell the robot to move
its wheel, well, it might
move forward.
Or the wheels might slip
or they might jam.
And in general, any action you take will
have some uncertainty in the real
world as to what exactly will happen.
In the case where your outcomes are
not worst case, they're just
controlled by some element of chance
that you can't predict, the values we
assign to various states should
take that into account.
And the values now should reflect
an average case rather than
a worst case scenario.
The worst case-- that's
minimax reasoning.
And today we're going to talk about
expectimax reasoning, where
essentially we replace all of
the mins with averages.
So let's look at this tree over here.
What happens on the left?
Well, the value of this left node should
clearly be 10 regardless of the
outcome, because both outcomes are 10.
How about on the right?
How much should we value
this node on the right?
Well, in minimax, it's only worth 9,
because that's what your opponent's
going to force.
But now it should probably be bigger
than 9, because we might get that 100.
How much bigger?
Well, it's going to depend on how likely
it is the 9 versus the 100
outcome is.
Let's say they're equally likely.
If they're are equally likely,
then it's going to be 54.5.
And then we should probably take the
right node, at least if they're
equally likely.
This is the basic idea
of expectimax search.
What we're going to compute in an
expectimax search is not the best
score under adversarial
play like minimax.
It's not a minimax value.
It's an expectimax value.
And that's the average score
under optimal play.
Why is it an average?
Because no matter how well you play, who
knows what's going to happen when
the dice roll?
So what we need to compute is whatever
actions are going to give me the best
outcome on average.
Max nodes are just like
a minimax search.
Chances are just like min nodes in the
sense that they're out of your
control, but rather than worst case
we're going to assume average case.
What we will be calculating here
is expected utilities.
If you think about the numbers at the
bottom of the tree as utilities for
the agent, and now we're taking averages
or expectations, this is this
idea of an expected utility.
You don't know how good this state is,
but you can talk about its average
utility to you.
And that's something if you remember way
back to the first lecture, and the
maximum expected utility principle,
we're finally getting
to be able to unpack.
All right, let's take a look at
why this is important again
in the Pac-Man demo.
And let's remember what happens
in this scenario here.
This scenario is, in fact, a very simple
game tree, because the agents
are so constrained.
And in a minimax scenario, Pac-Man
sees two options--
dive bomb the ghost or make
a try for the dots.
If the ghosts are adversarial, then you
should dive bomb the close ghost.
Because the game's going to end either
way, and in this variant of Pac-Man,
you would lose a point every turn.
And so, in fact, in the minimax
case, you dive bomb the ghost.
And, in fact, the game ends.
But we also realized that if those
ghosts were in fact random, o orange
ghost doesn't have a choice.
The only real choice is what
b;ue ghost is going to do.
So now Pac-Man should
think average case.
Pac-Man should think well, the
difference between going left and
right in the case that the blue ghost
moves up is not that great.
It's one point plus or minus, right?
But if the blue ghost happens to move
down, we can win the game and get a
huge bonus at the end.
And so in this case, even if we're
unsuccessful, even if in fact we are
not lucky, the action we should
take now to maximize our
utility is to go left.
So we're going to go left.
And well, it didn't work out.
So just because you were rational, just
because you did the action which
maximizes your expected utility, does
not mean you'll be successful.
You can still be unlucky.
But if we try this a bunch of times--
oh, please, random number generator--
it'll work out.
All right, so that's the case
for expectimax reasoning.
The expectimax pseudo code is
about what you would think.
We have a notion of a
value of the state.
It's no longer a minimax value.
It's now an expectimax value.
And how do we compute that value?
Well, we're going to
do it recursively.
If that state is terminal, then it's
marked with its utility and we just
return that.
If it's a Max state, meaning in the next
action is under the control of
the agent, then we max
over the children.
If the next agent is the expectation,
meaning this is the role of a die or
an uncertain opponent, then we should
take some kind of average.
Max looks just like it did before.
We started at negative infinity.
We look at all of the successors.
And one by one, we take
a maximum as we go.
What's new here is on the right.
How do we compute the average
value of a state?
So let's zoom in on that.
Well we have some state.
And we're going to take an
average of its children.
So how do we do that?
We loop over all the children.
For each child, we compute its value.
And we figure out the chance of that
child will happen from here.
And so far we've been acting like all
children are equal, but that's not
always going to be true in
every expectimax search.
So for each child, we compute a
probability and we compute a value.
We take the products,
and we add them up.
So, for example, here, we
might be in the state.
We're computing the expectation
of the children.
And so what we do is we visit
the children one by one.
And the first child has value eight,
but is 50 percent likely to occur.
Multiply those together--
1/3 times 24, 1/6 times negative 12.
And we get 10 there's the
computation for you.
So let's do an example of this.
So if we imagine all the children are
equally likely, we visit the first
child, and we see OK 3, OK 12, OK, 9.
We compute our average.
And we get what?
We get eight.
We go to the silent child child.
We see two, four, and six.
We compute the average.
We get four.
And we visit the last child--
we compute the average
and we get seven.
So looking down, yes, we'd like the
15, no, we wouldn't like the 0.
But we don't actually have
access to these directly.
We only get to choose amongst these
uncertain outcomes whose average
scores are listed here, and so what we
should do is we should take this
action and on average get eight
Now for minimax, we were able
to be pretty clever.
We were able to do the search, but often
we're able to just avoid doing
work by noticing that we had already
found a value so good or so bad that
the rest of the children didn't
even need to be explored.
Let's see whether or not we can recreate
this idea for expectimax.
So let's imagine we've looked at all
of the values under the left child,
and we've seen that it has value
8, and we've returned that.
Well, now max has an option
of expected value 8.
We go into the second child here
in the middle, and we look
at its first child.
And we see a 2.
So far, the state looks pretty bad.
maximum would not pick a 2.
But there are still children to check.
Now minimax, we were done.
Because it might get lower than
2, but it certainly wasn't
going to get higher.
This is an average.
Can this get higher than 2?
Absolutely.
How much higher?
Arbitrarily high.
So unless we actually have some kind of
bound on the range of these values,
we have to keep going, because even if
there's only one child left, and this
node looks terrible, that last child
could be a million dollars.
If you have bounds, that does change.
So in general, with expectimax, it's
just a lot harder to prune.
And the reason it's hard to prune is
because the values of a state--
it's kind of all of the
children tangled up.
You can no longer isolate individual
children and use them to bound the
rest very easily.
How do you use this in practice?
Well, it's a big game tree, so just like
in the minimax case, you can't
really search all the
way to the bottom.
This particular expectimax tree is a
little more complicated than the
alternating layers we've seen--
so that the agent-- in this case,
it's just shown as Pac-Man-- is
moving at the root.
And then the ghosts move.
And let's imagine they are
actually random shorts.
They picked randomly amongst
their legal actions.
In that case, we would actually have
two layers corresponding to the
sequence of two random ghost actions,
before Pac-Man moves again.
At the actual end of the game, we
know what the states are worth.
This is a game that's defined by its
score so you would just look at the
score of those states.
In any case, we're not going to be able
to go all the way down to the end
of the game, so at some point
we have to cut this off.
When we cut this process offered at some
limited depth, we don't actually
know what you will achieve on average
from that state under optimal play.
We like that.
We'd like to have some estimate of that
value instead, the true value but
true valley would take a lot of work to
compute, so we're going to plug-in
our best guess, just like
we did with minimax.
It's a little bit harder than it was in
minimax to get that process right.
And why is that?
Well let's think about minimax
again for a second.
And let's think about worst
case reasoning.
And let's think about the minimax
tree shown on the left here.
Minimax, this is pretty
straightforward.
We look at this tree and
we say all right.
On the left I get 0.
On the right, I get 20.
So I should go to the right.
What would happen if we got
those numbers wrong?
What would happen if we squared them?
Well, on the left, I would get 0,
and on the right I get 400.
So I should go right.
So nothing really changed.
minimax is really about the
ordering of the states.
As long as you get your numbers wrong
but you preserve that ordering,
minimax will be fine.
Expectimax is a little more fragile,
because of how these averages work.
So in particular, let's imagine these
are now average case expectimax trees,
and let's think again what happens.
Well, over on the left, the left branch
gives me 20, if the children
are even, and 25 over here.
What would I do?
I'd go right and get that 25.
How about in the left version where all
I've done is square the values?
I haven't changed their ordering?
What about the left?
Numbers are bigger, so it's 800.
And how about on the other side?
What are we going to get there?
That's 650.
What should we do?
We should go left.
So in this case, squaring these
things changed the answer.
Expectimax is much more dependent
on the scale and the
shape of these utilities.
And so it's something we're going to
have to get right if we want the
results to be meaningful.
The magnitudes are important,
not just their order.
And we're going to come back
to that later today.